Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Office records, 1933-2003 MVC0043.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Alumnae Office records
1933-2003
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary
Mount Vernon College
MVC0043.RG
6.75 Linear Feet 11 document boxes, 1 slim document box, and 1 flat box
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 and a two year junior college was added in 1927. The Junior College remained open until 1969, when Mount Vernon College became a four-year unversity. The university was an independent institution until 1999, when it became affilated with The George Washington University. This collection contains Alumnae Bulletins published by the Alumnae Office from July 1944 to Spring 2003, as well as Alumnae Directories published from 1933 to 2000. Popular topics addressed in Bulletins include messages from the Mount Vernon president, scrapbooks, Foxhall footnotes, commencements, class notes (including an updated alumnae directory), honor rolls, special sections for alumnae, reunions, calendars, features, in memoriams, and campus performances. The Directories contain information about the Alumnae Association and histories of Mount Vernon, as well as biographical listings, geographical indices, and class year indices of alumnae.
Conditions Governing Access Note
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Mount Vernon Seminary was officially established by Elizabeth Somers in 1875 with classes held at her residence on F Street; she named it after her brother's church in Baltimore, Mount Vernon Place Methodist. The Seminary began as a six year prepatory school, with four years of high school level classes, and two years of post-high school curriculum, calling it a "Family and Day School for Young Ladies." In order to graduate, students had to complete a formal process of "Senior Essays" in which they completed primary research and wrote on a current political or social topic, including such provocative issues as child labor, prohibition, poverty, and women's suffrage.
The school was moved to 1100 M. Street N.W. in 1900 and was once again moved in 1917 to a campus on Nebraska Avenue. In 1920 graduating class, eight women continued their education at universities such as the University of Wisconsin, Stanford, Northwestern and the University of Texas; by 1923 graduates were going to such other prestigious universities as UC-Berkeley, Columbia, Cornell, Smith College and the University of Chicago. Such advancements in higher education were uncommon for women of the day, but Mount Vernon was one of the premier prepatory institutions in the country.
In 1927, Mount Vernon established a Junior College, and with its establishment, students no longer had to complete six years of courses to receive a diploma; they graduated from the Seminary after four years and could continue on to the Junior College for two more years of college preparation. After World War II began, the U.S. Navy took over the campus in 1942 as a part of the war effort. During the 1943 academic year, the Seminary held classes in Spring Valley by leasing neighborhood residences. After receiving "just compensation" for their Nebraska Avneue campus, the school purchased 21 acres on Foxhall Road and surrounding areas in 1945, and had applied for accreditation to award Associates of Arts Degrees after completing two years of the Junior College.
Despite its expansion, by 1965 the Board of Trustees voted unanimously to dissolve the Seminary by 1969, as it could not financially support both institutions. During the 1960s, the Junior College developed new academic concentrations such as government, international relations and political science to reflect its location in the nation's capital. At the same time, it began to phase out its vocational training such as home economics and secretarial skills to make room for these higher education courses.
By 1973, the Board of Higher Education licensed the college to award Bachelor of Arts (BA) degrees such as Public Affairs, Government, Business Administration, Childhood, Special Education, and the Visual Arts, as well as honorary Doctor of Humane Letters and Juris Doctor Degrees; in 1976, the college received initial accreditation as a four-year college and was reaccredited ten years later. However, by 1996 the college announced a plan to affiliate with George Washington University and the last class of Mount Vernon College graduated in 1999. Today, as an affiliated campus of GWU, Mount Vernon offers special living accommodations, as well as learning and leadership programs for female students.
Arrangement Note
Organized into four series: Alumnae Bulletins, Alumnae Directories, Janet Maalouf papers, and Alumnae Office files and correspondence.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Scope and Contents Note
Series 1 contains Alumane Bulletins, which were published from 1944 to 2003. Bulletins were published both as magazines and newspapers throughout the publication's lifespan. Their content offers researchers the opportunity to learn about Mount Vernon Seminary and College alumnae, happenings on campus, and alumnae acitivities. Issues contain information on the alumnae association, calendars of events, reunions, commencements, alumane directories, features, campus life, and updates on the lives of alumnae (i.e. marriage, birth of children, and death). Photographs of events and alumnae are also heavily featured in issues.
Series 2 contains Alumnae Directories published between 1933 and 2000. Directories contain information about the Alumnae Association and histories of Mount Vernon, as well as biographical listings, geographical indices, and class year indices of alumnae.
Series 3 contains the papers of Janet Maalouf, Director of the Mount Vernon College Alumnae Relations Office. The series includes Alumnae Executive Council and Task Force records, alumnae contact information, and reunion files.
Series 4 contains files from the Mount Vernon Seminary and College alumnae office including annual reports and correspondence with alumnae.
Existence and Location of Copies Note
A set of Alumnae Bulletins is available in the Special Collections Research Center reading room.
Appraisal Note
Excess duplicates were removed.
Alumni & alumnae; Women -- Education; Publications; Women's colleges; Directories; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Alumnae Bulletins, 1944-2003; MVC0043, Series 1; Mount Vernon Seminary; 3 Linear Feet 4 document boxes and 1 flat box (Box 3, Box 2, Box 4, Box 1, Flat box 5)
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically, starting with July 1944 and ending with Spring 2003.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains Alumnae Bulletins from July 1944 to Spring 2003. Popular topics addressed in issues include messages from the Mount Vernon president, scrapbooks, Foxhall footnotes, commencements, class notes (updated alumnae directory), honor rolls, special sections for alumnae, reunions, calendars, features, in memoriams, and campus performances. The earliest issues of the Bulletin contain significantly less content than later issues. Bulletins contain information on both alumnae acitivities, as well as happenings around the Mount Vernon campus.
  Biographical/Historical Note
  One of the first alumnae publications, the Mount Vernon Seminary Bulletin, was first printed in 1944 by the Alumnae Office at Mount Vernon Seminary. Throughout its fifty-nine years of existence, the publication underwent a number of name changes and was published by different offices. The original purpose of the publication was to "keep you in touch with large aspects of school and Alumnae affairs at Mount Vernon Seminary." Even though the publication was originally meant to be a quarterly installment, it was only published bi-annually from 1948 to 1969. During that time, the name changed to The Bulletin of Mount Vernon Junior College and Seminary and Alumnae Association in 1960, and then to Mount Vernon Alumnae Bulletin in 1962. It was changed once again in 1971 to the Mount Vernon College Bulletin. During the early years of publication, the magazine was edited by the Alumnae Association, even though it was officially published by the Alumnae Office.
  Throughout the 1970s the Bulletin was published more frequently in a newspaper format. Beginning in 1975 it was published every six weeks during the academic year, but by 1979 it was reduced to a quarterly basis. For the first time in 1982, the Office of Institutional Advancement began to publish the Bulletin: Mount Vernon College. The office continued to publish the Bulletin on an annual basis until 1993 when the Office of External Relations published the Spring issue. The Fall 1993 issue was published by the Office of College Relations. In 1994 the publication underwent a name change and was re-titled Mount Vernon College Today, which was published by the Office of Alumnae Affairs. The office of publication switched frequently in more recent years: Office of College Relations (1995), Office of Alumnae Affairs (Winter 1995-2000), Office of Development and Alumnae Relations (2001), Office of Advancement (2002-2003)m Office of Alumni Programs (2004), Division of Advancement (2005-2006), Division of Development and Alumni Relations (2008-Present). Mount Vernon Today continues as an online publication and the bi-annual publication is available online since 2005: http://mvtoday.gwu.edu/.
  Publications; Alumni & alumnae; Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, November 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, March 1949 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1951 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1952 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1955 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1957 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1958 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1958 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1959 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1960 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1961 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1962 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Alumnae Newsletter, June-July 1970 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 1-2)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Alumnae Newsletter, June-July 1971 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 3-4)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1971 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Alumnae Bulletin Newsletter, Spring 1972 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 5-6)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Bulletin Newsletter, Fall 1972 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 7-8)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1973 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 9-10)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1975 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 11-12)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, February 1975 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 13)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, April 1975 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 14-15)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1975 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 16-17)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, August 1975 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 18-19)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, October 1975 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 20-21)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, February 1976 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 22-23)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, April 1976 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 24-25)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1976 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 26-27)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, November 1976 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 28-29)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, January 1977 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 30-31)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, June 1977 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 32-33)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1977 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 34-35)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1978 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 36-37)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, July 1978 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 38-39)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, November 1978 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 40-41)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1979 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 42)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, August 1979 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 43-44)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, December 1979 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 45-46)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1980 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 47-48)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1980 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 49-50)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1981 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 51-54)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1981 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 55-56)
  - Alumane Bulletin, Summer 1981 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 57-58)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, March 1982 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 59-60)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall/Winter 1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1987 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Winter 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1989 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Summer 1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1991 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Fall 1993 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Spring 1994 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall 1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Alumnae Bulletin, Honor Roll of Donors, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 1995 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 1995 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 1996 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 1997 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 1997 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 1997 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall 1997 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 1998 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring 1998 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 1998 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring 1999 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 1999 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 2000 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 2001 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 2001 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall 2001 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring 2002 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 2002 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall 2002 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring 2003 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 2004
  - Mount Vernon Today, Winter 2004
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring 2005 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 61)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Summer 2005 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 62)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring 2006 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 63)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall 2006 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 64)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring/Summer 2007 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 65)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall/Winter 2007 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 66)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall/Winter 2008 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 67)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Spring/Summer 2009 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 68)
  - Mount Vernon Today, Fall/Winter 2009 (Flat box 5, Loose-material 69)
- Alumnae Directories, 1933-2000; MVC0043, Series 2; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary; 2 document boxes and 1 slim document box (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  Arrangement Note
  Arranged chronologically.
  The first Alumnae Directory was published by the Alumnae Association of Mt. Vernon Seminary in 1933. In 1937, the first "official" directory was published by the Alumnae Office, who continued to publish directories until 2000. In addition to the biographical listings, geographical indices, and class year indices of alumnae, Directories published 1981 and later also contain information about the Alumnae Association, histories of Mount Vernon, and listings of faculty, Presidents of Mount Vernon, honary degree recipients, and distinguished alumnae awards recipients.
  Women -- Education; Women's colleges; Directories; Alumni & alumnae; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon Seminary, 1933-1934 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon Seminary, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon Seminary and Junior College, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, Soft cover, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, Hard cover, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, Blue Cover, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, Grey Cover, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, Greater Los Angeles, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, New York City Metro Area, 1992-1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, Green Cover, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon College, White Cover, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Directory: Mt. Vernon Seminary and College, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Janet Maalouf papers, 1982-1997; Series 3
  This series contains the papers of Janet Maalouf, Director of the Mount Vernon College Alumnae Relations Office. The series includes Alumnae Executive Council and Task Force records, alumnae contact information, and reunion files.
  Arrangement
  - Alumnae Executive Council records, 1982-1989; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Executive Council records, 1982-1989; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Task Force records, 1988-1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Alumnae Task Force records, 1988-1990; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - National Governing Board of the Alumnae Association records, 1991-1993; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - National Governing Board of the Alumnae Association records, 1991-1993; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 1992 reunion files, Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 1992 reunion files, Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 1992 reunion files, Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1993 reunion files, Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1993 reunion files, Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - 1993 reunion files, Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Alumnae contact information Atlanta-Washington, D.C. chapters, 1992-1993; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae contact information Japan-Sweden chapters, 1992-1993; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon Tennis Classic records, 1995; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Mount Vernon Tennis Classic records, Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Request for payment forms and receipts, 1995; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Mount Vernon alumnae contact information, 1996; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Mount Vernon alumnae contact information, 1996; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Mount Vernon alumnae contact information, 1996; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Janet Maalouf correspondence, 1997; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Alumnae office files and correspondence, 1953-1988; Series 4
  This series contains files from the Mount Vernon Seminary and College alumnae office including annual reports and correspondence with alumnae.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Alumnae Council booklets, 1953-1956; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Council booklets, 1957-1961; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae Office annual reports, 1976-1984; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Class reporter--Mount Vernon College classes of 1936-1963, 1965-1973; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Class reporter--Mount Vernon Seminary classes of 1949-1964, 1965-1973 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Reunion directory, 1988; Series 4 (Box 13, Folder 6)